Guide to the Agenda Records
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Agenda records
1914-1985
1969-1984
GEN MSS 87
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
55.21
(83 boxes)
The Agenda Records consist of materials from the production files of Agenda magazine from volume 7, number 3 (1969) through volume 37, number 4 (2000), with related financial records, and additional materials from editor William Cookson's files. Writings include works submitted for publication in Agenda or the Agenda Editions and consist of articles, poems, and reviews in holograph, typescript, galley and proof form, many bearing annotations by editor or author. The production files contain advertising copy, notes, computer disks, and galleys and proofs of issues. The correspondence is between William Cookson and contributors, his associate editor Peter Dale, and other business associates. Additional papers include business papers, photographs, and a small number of printed works. Also included are papers concerning William Cookson's writing and editing activities outside of his work at Agenda.
Agenda (London, England)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Anthony Garnett on the Edwin J. Beinecke Fund, 1984-2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 58: Restricted Fragile Material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Box 82: (computer disks): Restricted Fragile Material. Reference copies of electronic files are available. Consult Access Services for further information.
AGENDA
The poetry journal Agenda was established in 1959 as a revival of an earlier publication, Four Pages. Agenda 's founding editor was William C. Cookson; the associate editor was Edmund Gray. Gray was eventually replaced by Michael O'Higgins. In 1962 Agenda was reorganized and the magazine's editorial policy was reevaluated. At that time, Cookson appointed Peter Dale associate editor and chief poetry reviewer.
Agenda began publication out of New College, Oxford; throughout most of its history, however, it has been produced in London. At first issued monthly, by 1961 two numbers comprised one issue and eventually Agenda became a quarterly. Beginning in 1965 Agenda received regular grants from the Arts Council of Great Britain; this ongoing support has been a contributing factor in the success of the magazine.
Cookson initially based Agenda 's editorial policy on the literary and economic ideas of Ezra Pound. Over time he came to believe that the magazine was straying from its original direction and, in 1962, Cookson decided that Agenda would "contain only the best poetry." The magazine would also include a regular review section, "criteria of which would be based upon Pound's early basic rules of criticism", and articles on both neglected poets and those with "inflated" reputations.
By 1965 the magazine had adopted a large format with cover lettering by David Jones. Entire issues were often devoted to the work of a single poet (David Jones, Wyndham Lewis, and Ezra Pound) or to a specific type of poetry (French poetry, American poetry, or verse drama). These issues sometimes employed guest editors, such as Donald Davie and Charles Tomlinson.
In 1971 Cookson and Peter Dale began the publication of "Agenda Editions," the purpose of which was to publish in book format the same type of poetry as appeared in the magazine. The first "Edition" issued was Peter Dale's translation of François Villon's The Legacy and Other Poems. Subsequent volumes include The Roman Quarry, by David Jones, Mortal Fire, by Peter Dale, Footsteps on Snow and The Curving Shore, both by Anne Beresford, and The Mystery of the Charity of Charles Peguy, by Geoffrey Hill.
Since William Cookson's death in 2003, Agenda has been published under the editorial guidance of Patricia McCarthy.
Scope and Contents
The Agenda Records, 1914-2001, consist of materials from the production files of volume 7, number 3 (1969) through volume 37, number 4 (2000) of Agenda magazine, related financial and other records, and additional materials from editor William Cookson's files.
The collection is arranged into four series and three later groupings. Series I, Writings, (Boxes 1-31), is made up of works submitted for publication in Agenda or the "Agenda Editions." Series II, Production files, (Boxes 32-39), contains the galleys, page proofs, and other production material remaining from the work files for Volume 7:3 (1969) - Volume 22 (1984) once writings (Series I) and the correspondence (Series III) had been culled and arranged separately. The correspondence in Series III consists chiefly of exchanges between the two principal editors, William Cookson and Peter Dale, and various supporters, business associates and contributors to Agenda and "Agenda Editions." Series IV, Additional Papers, (Boxes 53-56), contains papers and writings of William Cookson, which do not strictly relate to Agenda, as well as other financial records, printed material and photographs. Groupings V-VII represent later additions to the collection acquired between 1994 and 2001 and are comprised of material similar in nature and scope to that found in Series I-IV, including writings, production files, correspondence, and other papers related to Agenda and "Agenda Editions."
Series I, Writings, consists of articles, poems and reviews in various stages of completion (holographs, typescripts, galleys and proofs), many bearing holograph corrections or annotations by William Cookson or the author. Works to be found in this series include Michael Alexander's reviews of books about Ezra Pound, as well as Alexander's poem, "Of Green Fields"; an article by Noel Stock entitled "Literature and Economics: A New Correlation"; miscellaneous notes by Dorothy Pound; translations of "Cantos LXII and LXIII," by Richard Reid; "The Hunt," a poem by David Jones and an essay by Arthur Giardelli on Jones's "Trystan ac Esyllt;" Donald Davie's poems, "England" and "Ornithology"; poetry by Ronald Duncan, including "Letter to Ezra"; classical poetry in translation by Humphrey Clucas; poems translated from Persian and Arabic by Omar Pound and a large number of Editorials written for Agenda by William Cookson. Material from the files of "Agenda Editions" includes an incomplete holograph of The Kensington Mass, by David Jones; The Curving Shore and Footsteps on Snow, by Anne Beresford; and Xenia and Motets, by Eugenio Montale.
Additional authors represented in the Writings series include Michael Alexander, Sabine Awiszus, John Bayley, William Bedford, Anne Beresford, Thomas Blackburn, Robert Bly, Keith Bosley, Basil Bunting, John Cayley, Cal Clothier, Humphrey Clucas, Michael Collier, William Cookson, Arthur Cooper, Peter Dale, Donald Davie, Peter Dent, Ronald Duncan, Reginald Gibbons, René Hague, Michael Hamburger, John Heath-Stubbs, Geoffrey Hill, Peter Jay, David Jones, Roland John, Peter Levi, Hugh MacDiarmid, William S. Milne, Penelope Palmer, John Peck, Ezra Pound, Michael Reck, C. H. Sisson, Charles Tomlinson, Peter Whigham and Louis Zukofsky.
Series II, Production Files, contains advertising copy, table of contents pages, notes, galleys and proofs of entire issues, arranged chronologically by issue number, including proofs of grouped responses to questionnaires on a variety of topics, which the editors of Agenda magazine frequently sent to individual poets and writers. Drafts of individual's responses to these questionnaires, however, were transferred to Series I, Writings, where they can be found filed under the name of the respondent.
Series III, Correspondence, consists primarily of letters exchanged between William Cookson and various supporters and business associates, as well as contributors to Agenda and the "Editions." Correspondence with Peter Dale, the associate editor, and Donald Davie, a guest editor, also is included. Correspondents discuss editorial aspects of writings contributed to the magazine, but also day-to-day business and news of a more personal nature.
Agenda 's early years are well documented in this series. The files contain letters of rejection, letters asking for submissions from established poets, and requests for permissions to publish. There is correspondence in which marketing strategies are discussed, as well as letters soliciting subscriptions. Finally, correspondence between Cookson and the Arts Council of Great Britain chronicles Agenda 's relationship with the Arts Council and traces the growth of its financial support. The correspondence of Associate Editor Peter Dale includes discussions of specific articles and poems as well as matters of general editorial policy.
Agenda was based upon suggestions made by Ezra Pound in 1958. Although Cookson continued to correspond with Pound throughout the magazine's early years, the collection contains only copies of Cookson's outgoing letters; there are no letters from Pound. (Letters from Dorothy Pound, which are present, include her own comments on Agenda .)
In his earliest letters to Pound, Cookson outlines his plans for Agenda; later letters reveal his (Cookson's) growing concern that Agenda was straying from Pound's philosophy, and expresses his view that editorial restructuring was necessary. In several letters Cookson solicits contributions from Pound to be published in Agenda; he also requests permission to publish Pound's work.
Two other early supporters and contributors to Agenda, Michael Alexander and Peter Russell, also are well represented in the correspondence files. In his letters, Alexander suggests names of individuals Cookson might wish to contact for help with Agenda. He discusses his own submissions and also comments on Pound and his work. Russell, a bookseller, publisher, poet, and professor, advertised in Agenda and contributed his own poetry. His letters offer comments on the magazine's format, criticism of poetry and articles, and advice on dealing with publishers and printers. Due to disagreements with Cookson over the acceptance of his own work, Russell eventually stopped contributing.
Over the years Cookson and Agenda established contacts with many other presses and publishers and these, too, are well documented in the correspondence files. The letters between Cookson and Michael Schmidt of Carcanet Press concern the inclusion of Agenda and "Agenda Editions" in Carcanet's catalogues as well as possible marketing strategies. In addition to requests for review copies, correspondence between Cookson and Peter du Sautoy of Faber and Faber makes reference to advertising, plans to publish a book by David Jones, and problems encountered in publishing the works of Ezra Pound. The Faber files also trace the publication history of the Cookson edition of The Selected Prose of Ezra Pound 1909-1965.
In Cookson's correspondence with James Laughlin of New Directions one again finds discussions of difficulties encountered in efforts to publish works by Ezra Pound. There are inquiries about available Cantos, discussions of copyrights to the books of prose, and remarks on difficulties that arose at the time of Pound's death. There is also correspondence dealing with permission to publish poems by William Carlos Williams in a special edition of Agenda, and letters discussing poems Laughlin himself submitted to Agenda.
In addition to tracking the role early supporters and business associates played in Agenda 's development and eventual success, the correspondence series documents the on-going relationship between Agenda and the many poets whose works were published in the magazine or in the "Editions." Among the poets who figure most prominently in this series one finds Hugh MacDiarmid, Peter Levi, C. H. Sisson, Charles Tomlinson, Peter Whigham, and Louis Zukofsky. Letters from Basil Bunting reveal his thoughts on the classical and myth issues of Agenda and his opinions on the younger generation of poets. The Scottish poet Tom Scott suggests a Scottish number of Agenda, and comments on Ezra Pound and possible contributions to Agenda, such as the poem "Auld-farrant Gecks."
In several cases, individual poets achieved particular prominence and entire issues or volumes of the "Agenda Editions" were devoted to their work. Of these featured poets, David Jones is particularly well represented. In addition to the letters from Jones himself, he is also a frequent subject in the correspondence of others. The correspondence of René Hague, for example, concerns articles on Jones and discussions of Jones's The Kensington Mass and Hague's book Dai Greatcoat. There is also a manuscript of "A Note on Anamnesis". Other Jones scholars whose correspondence can be found in this series are David Blamires, Keith Bosley, Louis Bonnerot, Arthur Giardelli, Tony Stoneburner, and Colin Wilcockson.
Other noteworthy correspondents in this series include Sabine Awiszus, D. G. Bridson, Thomas Carter, Guy Davenport, Barbara Eastman, Eric Homberger, Jamila Ismail, Hugh Kenner, Eva Hesse, Harry Meacham, Desmond O'Grady, John Peck, Daniel Pearlman, Sister Mary Bernetta Quinn, and Noel Stock.
Series IV, Additional Papers, contains further materials pertaining to the financial and other administrative concerns of Agenda magazine, and some additional writings and personal papers of William Cookson.
The Business Papers subseries includes additional information on subscriptions, marketing and the Arts Council of Great Britain. There are also invoices and statements from The Poets and Painters Press detailing the costs of publishing Agenda from 1967-1977. A subseries of Printed Works includes a list of letters by David Jones compiled by Tony Stoneburner in 1977 and a copy of Four Pages, number 11, annotated by Henry Swabey. The Photographs subseries includes pictures of works by David Jones and Wyndham Lewis, and portraits of Basil Bunting, Robert Lowell and Hugh MacDiarmid.
The section devoted to William Cookson reflects his writing and editing activities outside of Agenda. Included are drafts of Cookson's A Guide to the Cantos of Ezra Pound; A Commentary on the Cantos of Ezra Pound and the introduction to Selected Prose 1909-1965.
Box 57 contains Oversize material which is arranged in series order, including correspondence and writings. Box 58, Restricted Fragile Papers, consists of originals for which preservation copies have been made.
V. August 1994 Acquisition contains production material for volume 21, number 2 (1983) to volume 30, number 3 (1992-1993) of Agenda, production material for "Agenda Editions," writings, including typescripts and proofs, and correspondence, including William Cookson's correspondence with Peter Dale, Kathleen Raine, and other poets and critics.
VI. November 2001 Acquisition contains production material for volume 21, number 1 (1983) to volume 37, number 1 (1999) of Agenda, writings, including typescripts and proofs, correspondence, electronic files, and other papers.
VII. October 2007 Acquisition contains production material for volume 37, numbers 2-4 (1999-2000), correspondence, and writings.
Arrangement
Organized into four series and three groupings: Series I. Writings, 1925-1984. Series II. Production Files, 1969-1984. Series III. Correspondence, 1958-1985. Series IV. Additional Papers, 1914-1983. V. August 1994 Acquisition, 1978-1994. VI. November 2001 Acquisition, 1972-2000. VII. October 2007 Acquisition, 1983-2001.
Agenda (London, England); Authors and publishers; English literature -- 20th Century; Little magazines -- England; Periodicals -- Publishing -- Finance; Periodicals -- England; Poets, English -- Archives; Publishers and publishing; Born digital; Electronic documents; Little magazines; Periodicals; Photographs; Critics; Poets; Alexander, Michael J.; Bedford, William, 1943-; Beresford, Anne, 1929-; Bunting, Basil, 1900-; Clucas, Humphrey, 1941-; Cookson, William, 1939-; Dale, Peter, 1938-; Davie, Donald, 1922-1995; Dent, Peter; Hamburger, Michael, 1924-2007; Hill, Geoffrey, 1932-2016; John, Roland; Jones, David, 1895-1974; Levi, Peter, 1931-; Lewis, Wyndham, 1882-1957; MacDiarmid, Hugh, 1892-1978; Massey, Alan, 1932-; Peck, John, 1941-; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972; Sisson, C. H. (Charles Hubert), 1914-2003; Tomlinson, Charles, 1927-2015; Whigham, Peter; Wright, David, 1920-1994; Agenda editions (London, England)
- Writings, 1925-1984; Series I; 15.5; (31 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I is arranged alphabetically by author. Material which has been translated appears under the name of the original author, where known. Material for which the author is unknown appears under the name of the translator. Material with no identified author or translator is found at the end of the series, alphabetically arranged by title. All titles have been transcribed as found on the originals, including punctuation.
  - Adams, John J.
    - "To. W. L. on his Human Age, spoken printed and bound," typescript, annotated, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ai, Ch'ing (Ai Qing)
    - "Dayanhe-My Nurse," "Snow Falls on the Chinese Land," "The Woman Mending Clothes," "A Girl Taking Aim" and "Your Dream," unidentified translator, printed version, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - [32 Poems], translated by Marilyn Chin, typescript, with biographical material, 1980-81 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Akhamatova, Anna
    - "Requiem," translated by D. M. Thomas, typescript, carbon, ca.1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Requiem," fragment, translated by Robert Chandler, typescript, photocopy, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Alberti, Rafael
    - "The Murdered Poet Returns," translated by Michael Hamburger, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Alcman
    - "Partheneia (Maiden Songs)," translated by Peter Jay
      - Typescript, corrected, ca. 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - Galley, with author's corrections, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Alder, David
    - [Seven poems], typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Alecsandri, Vasile
    - "Miorita"
      - Translated by W. D. Snodgrass, Simone Draghici and Ioan Popa, typescript, photocopy, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
      - Printed page, photocopy, in Romanian, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Alexander, Michael
    - [Review] The Art of the Real. Poetry in England and America since 1939, by Eric Homberger
      - Typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - Galley, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - [Review] Collected Early Poems of Ezra Pound, edited by M. J. King
      - Typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Galley, with author's corrections, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - Galley, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "Do you remember that?"
      - Typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - Galley, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - [Review] "Donald Davie's Essex Poems ," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - "Eight Old English Riddles"
      - Printed version, photocopy, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
      - Galleys, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - [Review] The Elek Book of Oriental Verse, edited by Keith Bosley
      - Typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Galley, with author's corrections, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - [Review] Ezra Pound, The London Years 1908-1920, edited by Philip Grover
      - Typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Galley, with author's corrections, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
      - Galley, corrected (Box 1, Folder 26)
        With: review of A Student's Guide to the Selected Poems of Ezra Pound, galley.
    - "Ezra Pound's 'Seafarer'"
      - Typescript, photocopy, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
      - Galley, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - "G. S. Fraser," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - "Li Po and Tu Fu"
      - Typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
      - Galley, with author's corrections, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - [Review] "Mercian Hymns, by Geoffrey Hill"
      - Typescript, corrected (Box 1, Folder 32)
      - Galley, with author's corrections, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - "Of Green Fields. For Alexis Tolstoy," typescript, 1965 Mar 15 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - [Review] "On David Jones's Letters, Man, Poetry, and the BBC"
      - Typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
      - Galley, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - "Pound's Sense of Humour"
      - Typescript, photocopy, 1979 Mar 30 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      - Galleys, corrected, 1979 Mar 30 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - [Review] "Provence and Pound," typescript, corrected, 1980 Jul 1 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - "Six Anglo-Saxon Riddles," printed version, photocopy, undated (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - [Review] A Student's Guide to the Selected Poems of Ezra Pound, by Peter Brooker, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - [Review] "Taste," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Twelve Poems, [Agenda Editions] galley with author's corrections, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Alexander, Michael, (translator)
    - Beowulf, typescript, with corrections, [partial translation], n.y. May 28 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - al Seyyab, Badr Shekir
    - "The Book of Job," translated by Desmond O'Grady, autograph ms., photocopy, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - al-Udhari, Abdulla, (translator)
    - "Six Arab Poems," typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Alvarez, A.
    - "The Waterfall," typescript, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Anderson, Nicholas
    - [Review] "Ezra Pound and Music: The Complete Criticism ," edited by R. Murray Schafer
      - Typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 48)
      - Galley, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Andrews, Karin
    - [Review] A Lifelong House, Poems by Lotte Kramer
      - Typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 50)
      - Galley, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Apollinaire, Guillaume
    - "From the Firing Line," translated by Val Warner, typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - "Twelve Poems," translated by Val Warner
      - Typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 53)
      - Galley, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Arghezi, Tudor
    - "Mourning Doliu," translated by Anne Beresford, typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - "Three Poems," translated by Anne Beresford, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - "Two Poems," translated by Virgil Nemoianu and Peter Joy, typescript, carbon and photocopy, undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Arnault, Daniel
    - "L'aura amara," printed version, photocopy, undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Ashbery, John
    - "Two Poems," typescript, photocopy and printed version, photocopy, undated (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Ashdarn, John
    - ["?Sequence,"] typescript, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - "Wish," typescript, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Untitled poem, typescript, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Astley, Neil
    - "Three Poems," galley, undated (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - "Two Poems"
      - Galleys, with author's corrections, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 64)
        With: ANS from Neil Astley to William Cookson, 1980 Sep 9
  - Auden, W. H.
    - [Response to Agenda questionnaire]
      - Typescript, corrected and signed, undated (Box 1, Folder 65)
      - Galley, with author's corrections, undated (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Awiszus, Sabine
    - [Review] "The Poet Professorially Cross Examined"
      - Typescript, corrected, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 67)
      - Galley, corrected, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - "Statements on Pound's Prose"
      - Typescript, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 69)
      - Galley, corrected, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - B., A.
    - [Review] "Joseph Brodsky: Selected Poems," typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - [Review] "Nineteenth Century Russian Literature: Studies of Russian Writers, edited by John Fennell...," typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - [Review] "Red Earth," typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 73)